Guide to the Czechoslovak Nationality Room Committee Collection, 1925-2013 UA.40.05
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Czechoslovak Nationality Room Committee Collection
1925-2013
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Program. Czechoslovak Nationality Room Committee
UA.40.05
5 Linear Feet (10 boxes)
The Czechoslovak Nationality Room Committee contains correspondence, photographs, drawings, minutes and publicity relating to the Czechoslovak Room's construction, as well as committee functions subsequent to the room's dedication. After the dedication in 1939, the committee shifted its efforts to the organization of local cultural events and the sponsorship of an annual exchange scholarship. The bulk of the collection dates to the second half of the twentieth century and includes committee correspondence, programs, publicity, essays and other papers relating to its latter role in scholarship and cultural activities. Digital reproductions of all of the photographs are available online.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Deposited by Cristina Lagnese in June 2013.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series according to subject. Series I contains four subseries ordered by genre. Series II contains three subseries arranged by genre.
Series I. Room Construction and Dedication
Series II. Committee Administration
History
The Czechoslovak Nationality Room was dedicated in 1939 as one of the original 19 Nationality Classrooms in the University of Pittsburgh's Cathedral of Learning. The Nationality Rooms Committees formed at the invitation of Chancellor John G. Bowman and Program Director Ruth Crawford Mitchell, who envisioned the rooms as apolitical monuments to the cultural roots of Pittsburgh. The completion of the Czechoslovak Room, like all Nationality Rooms, was an international effort. Committees in both Pittsburgh and Prague jointly oversaw the room's design, construction and decoration in a traditional, folk-inspired aesthetic. Ruth Crawford Mitchell spearheaded early construction efforts at the University of Pittsburgh, while Alice Garrigue Masaryk advised affairs in Prague, where she engaged architect Bohumil Slama, artists Karel and Marie Svolinsky, and other contributing artisans. After the dedication of its classroom, the Czechoslovak Room committee continued its role as an arbiter of cultural exchange, both locally and internationally. The committee sponsors one of the annual exchage scholarship provided by the Nationality Rooms program. Members also participate in the organization of local cultural events, such as concerts, lectures, memorials, and community gatherings.
Previous Citation
Czechoslovak Nationality Room Committee Collection, 1925-2013, UA.40.05, University of Pittsburgh Archives
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of the photographs in the collection are available online.
Scope and Content Notes
The Czechoslovak Nationality Room Committee collection incorporates correspondence, photographs and minutes documenting the room's construction and dedication, as well as administrative materials from World War II to present, after the dedication of the Czechoslovak Room at the Cathedral of Learning in 1939. During the war, the running affairs of the committee primarily included donation and relief efforts for civilians and soldiers overseas. The bulk of the collection covers the second half of the twentieth century, and is concerned with its participatory and organizational roles in the Nationality Rooms international exchange scholarship program and local cultural events. Materials from the collection represent committee meetings, planning of local Czech and Slovak cultural and memorial gatherings, entertaining national and international dignitaries and visitors, maintaining the classroom and support of the committee scholarship. Included are correspondence, programs, invitations, essays, publicity, transcripts of speeches and remarks, as well as as incomplete sets of minutes and committee newsletters.
Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Classrooms -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Slovak Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Czech Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; University of Pittsburgh; Clippings (Information artifacts); Minutes (Administrative records); Financial records; Photographs; Correspondence; Architectural drawings (Visual works); Masaryk, Jan; Masaryk, Alice Garrigue; University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Program; University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Program. Czechoslovak Nationality Room Committee; Nationality Rooms (Cathedral of Learning, Pittsburgh, Pa.); Getting, Milan; Svolinský, Karel; Mitchell, Ruth Crawford; Sláma, Bohumil; Masaryk, T. G. (Tomáš Garrigue)
- Room Construction and Dedication, 1925-1957; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The bulk of the materials within this series predate the room's construction in 1939, and contain local and international correspondence, architectural renderings and artist's sketches relating to committee and organization and the planning of the rooms. Also included is a subseries of photographs depicting committee members, events and meetings, as well as the Czechoslovak Room and interior details.
  - General Correspondence, 1.
    This subseries contains correspondence and associated papers exchanged by committee members and Nationality Rooms Program officers, such as Ruth Crawford Mitchell, relating to room and committee organization.
    - General Correspondence, 1925-1927 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - General Correspondence, 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - General Correspondence, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Dr. Benes' Visit to the University of Pittsburgh, May 13, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - General Correspondence, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - General Correspondence, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - General Correspondence, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Publicity Materials, 2.
    This subseries contains publicity materials relating to the Czechoslovak Room, the Czechoslovak Room Committee, and the Nationality Rooms Program.
    - Publicity Materials, 1925-1939 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1925-1939 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - International and Architectural Correspondence, 3.
    This subseries contains correspondence between committee organizers Ruth Crawford Mitchell and Alice Garrigue Masaryk, Pittsburgh and Prague committee members, and Prague-based architect Bohumil Slama.
    - International and Architectural Correspondence, 1927-1929 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - International and Architectural Correspondence, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - International and Architectural Correspondence, 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - International and Architectural Correspondence, 1933-1935 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - International and Architectural Correspondence, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - International and Architectural Correspondence, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - International and Architectural Correspondence, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Czechoslovak Room Dedication, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Photographs and Drawings, 4.
    This subseries contains decorative sketches, architectural renderings, and photographs of the Pittsburgh Czechoslovak committee, its events, the finished classroom and interior details. All of the photos have been scanned and available online as part of the University of Pittsburgh Historic Photographs collection.
    - Czechoslovak Room Committee (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Czechoslovak Room Architect and Artist Drawings (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Czechoslovak Room Decoration and Interior Details (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Czechoslovak Classroom (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Czechoslovak Room Dedication, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Dr. Benes' Visit to the University of Pittsburgh, May 13, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Minutes, 1927-1939; 5.
    This subseries contains a bound volume of committee minutes and financial statements covering the planning and construction of the Czechoslovak Room.
    - Minutes, 1927-1939 (Box 9, Volume 1)
  - Committee Archives Boxes, 6.
    This subseries consists of the four boxes that served as the original enclosures for the records of the Czechoslovak Nationality Room Committee. These ornate containers were likely to be kept within the Nationality Room, but as the room began to collect artifacts for display, there was no longer room for the records and they were transferred to the University Archives.
    - Box for "General Correspondence, Dedication Ceremony and Visit of Dr. Benes" (Box 10, Volume 1)
    - Box for "Foreign Correspondence, Prague Committee and Architect" (Box 10, Volume 2)
    - Box for "Drawings and Photographs" (Box 10, Volume 3)
    - Box for "Publicity Material and Newspaper Clippings" (Box 10, Volume 4)
- Committee Administration, II.
  This series contains materials that postdate the dedication of the Czechoslova Room in 1939. At this time, the committee's attention turned to the organization of cultural events in Pittsburgh, participation in European relief efforts and national Czechoslovak associations, and the sponsorship of exchange scholarships for the Nationality Rooms Program. Included are correspondence, incompete newsletters, publicity, memos, speeches and essays.
  - Running Affairs, 1.
    This subseries contains materials relating to the general running of committee affairs. These records primarily include correspondence and memos, but are interspersed with committee newsletters, member lists, as well as well as an incomplete set of minutes, programs, and invitations for committee meetings, associated organizations and efforts.
    - Hunt, "Thomas Garrigue Masaryk" Brochure, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Committee Members, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Czechoslovak Committee, 1952-1962 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Czechoslovak Cabinet and Archives, 1959-1968 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Czechoslovak Committee, 1943-1971 (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
    - Committee Correspondence, 1959-1971 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Committee Members, 1966-1971 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Czechoslovak Room Maintenance (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Committee Correspondence, 1974-1978 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    - Czechoslovak Committee Gifts, 1945-1981 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Committee Correspondence, 1977-1981 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Czechoslovak Committee, 1979-1982 (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
    - Czechoslovak Committee, 1979-1982 (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
    - Czechoslovak Committee, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Stanley Postrednick Correspondence, 1979-1986 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Czechoslovak Committee, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Czechoslovak Committee, 1971-1989 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Czechoslovak Committee, 1990-1992 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Czechoslovak Committee, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Czechoslovak Committee, 1995-1997 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Czechoslovak Committee, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Czechoslovak Committee, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Czechoslovak Committee, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Czechoslovak Committee, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Czechoslovak Committee, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Czechoslovak Committee, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Czechoslovak Committee, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Czechoslovak Committee, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Czechoslovak Committee, 2006 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Czechoslovak Committee, 2007 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    - Czechoslovak Committee Newsletters (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Events, 2.
    This subseries contains papers relating to specific committee events, Czechoslovak Room projects, members and donations. Records include correspondence, transcripts, invitations and publicity.
    - Committee WWII Relief Effort, 1943-1945 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Masaryk Memorial Service, 1948-1956 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Czechoslovak Room Redecoration, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Masa Riegl Memorial, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Special Events, 1958-1968 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Committee Events, 1959-1968 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Karel Svolinsky Visit, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Committee Events, 1970-1974 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Masaryk Papers Presentation, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Committee Events, 1988-1994 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Publicity, 1991-2000 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Publicity, 1988-2001 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Pittsburgh Agreement, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Subject Files, 3.
    This subseries contains files originally compiled alphabetically by individual or subject name for Nationality Rooms Program office reference purposes. Included are speech transcripts, historical and biographical essays and notes, memorial programs, correspondence and publicity.
    - Czechoslovak Room, Books and Articles, 1990-2001 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Czechoslovak Room, Charles IV Brocade (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Czechoslovak Room, Charles University (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Czechoslovak Room, Culture, 1988-1996 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Folk Dances, Czechoslovak (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Gaul, James, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Getting Family Memoir, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 3-4)
    - Czechoslovak, History, 1974-1996 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Czechoslovak, Holidays, 1953-1973 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Macek, Josef, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Masaryk, Thomas, 1993-2001 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Riegl, Masa, 1964-1967 (Box 9, Folder 9)